PRAVEEN KUMAR NEELAPPA

768 E41 ST Erie PA 16504 | 304-777-3710 | pnkumar@outlook.com | www.pnkumar.com

PROFILE

Experienced graduate with a demonstrated history of working in Data Analytics, Data Capture, and Data Consolidation. Skilled in Python, R, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Agile Methodologies, and Document Management System. Strong domain knowledge in financial(banking) and retail industries. Currently a candidate for a Master of Science (M.S.) in Data Science from Mercyhurst University with anticipated graduation date of May 2018

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer - Tesco Bengaluru

April 2015 - January 2016

I was responsible for creating statistical reports on weekly sales data. Used machine learning algorithms for prediction number of pages to be scanned and used Tableau, Excel and R for reporting the finding to management. Other responsibility includes but not limited to onboarding new customer into production environment from developing, testing and deployment.

Skills acquired: R, Excel, Tableau, SQL and Python (numpy, pandas)

System Engineer – Iron Mountain

December 2013 - April 2015

I was responsible for investigating and resolving major production issues. It involved interacting with technical managers on analyzing the metadata of the application, system and customer feedback to analyze performance of production environment. The result was customized to different teams and reported with the recommendation.

Skills acquired: Kofax Mobile Capture, Excel, R, Tableau and SQL

System Engineer – Iron Mountain

November 2011 – July 2013

As a Systems Engineer in DMS L2 Support, I was part of a team that handled infrastructure, document management and various issues of scanning centers across USA and EU in the Kofax environment that processed a customer's document.

Skills acquired: Kofax 10, KCNS, Kofax Web Capture and SQL

Associate Engineer – Tata Consultancy Services

September 2007 – May 2009

Worked in enterprise delivery team where the documents from USAA are sent to customer through USAA Document Online (UDO). Worked with the team to develop a program to deliver the document to UDO after packing and tracking the document

Skills acquired: Java/J2EE, Eclipse, DB2, Oracle, Captiva, Rightfax, Crystal Report, IBM Tivoli Document

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Machine Learning: Classification, Regression, Clustering, Feature engineering

Statistical Methods: Time series, Regression models, Hypothesis Testing and Confidence Intervals, Principal Component Analysis and Dimensionality Reduction

Software and Programming Languages: Python (scikit-learn, numpy, scipy, pandas), R (Caret, dplyr), Tableau, SQL and Linux

EDUCATION

Mercyhurst University Fall 2016-Spring 2018

Master of Science in Data Science

National Institute of Technology, Karnataka Aug 2003-May 2007

Bachelor of Technology in Metallurgy and Materials Science engineering

CERTIFICATIONS

Applied Machine Learning with Python

ITIL V3 Certification

Kofax Capture 10/ KOFAX Capture Network Server 10

VOLUNTEERISM & CLUBS

President of Data Science Club, Mercyhurst University

Aug 2017 – till date

Chairman of Daksha CSR wing of Iron Mountain Dec 2011 to April 2015

Founder/President H2O Charitable Trust(NGO) Sept 2007 to April 2011

Convener of Artist Forum, National Institute of Technology Aug 2005 to April 2006

LINKS

kaggle

Project and Tech article www.pnkumar.com

Github https://github.com/alwaysarian

LinkedIn https://www.linkedin.com/in/praveen-kumar-n-58957bab/

Kaggle https://www.kaggle.com/pnkumar

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Estimating Ancestry using Neural Network analysis of Dental Morphology

Code & Findings: https://github.com/alwaysarian/Advance-Analytical-Technique

Recommendation of Beer using clustering (Unsupervised learning)

Code & Findings: https://github.com/alwaysarian/beer

Comparative Analysis of Graduate Female in India using Data Visualization

Code & Findings: https://github.com/alwaysarian/IndiaEducationData

Effect of Technology on Development of Countries using STATA

Findings: http://www.pnkumar.com/2017/09/13/effect-of-technology-on-development-of-countries/

Cyber Education - A Key to Reducing Human Error in Cyber Security

Findings: http://www.pnkumar.com/2017/09/13/cyber-education-a-key-to-reducing-human-error-in-cybersecurity/

Analytical Report - Investment in South African Mining Industry

Findings: http://www.pnkumar.com/2017/09/15/analytical-report-investment-in-south-african-mining-industry/

The Great North Korean Debate: Do you argue like an Imperialist?

Co-Authored with Dr.Michael Lamm (Text Analysis of news article for the International Studies Association Conference, Washington D.C., October 13- 15, 2017)

Findings: http://www.pnkumar.com/2018/01/14/the-great-north-korean-debate-do-you-argue-like-an-imperialist/

Online Competition Ranking

DrivenData | United Nations Millennium Development Goals | Rank 21(Top 2%)

DrivenData | Warm Up: Predict Blood Donations | Rank 232(Top 6%)

DrivenData | Pump it Up: Data Mining the Water Table | Rank 300(Top 7%)